Guide to the Aileen St. John-Brenon Papers 1920-1947 MS 3045
New-York Historical Society
Aileen St. John-Brenon papers
1920-1947
New-York Historical Society
St. John-Brenon, Aileen, 1894-1967
MS 3045
1.04 Linear feet (3 boxes)
Papers, correspondence, and ephemera of American music critic, and theatrical and film publicist Aileen St. John-Brenon (1894–1967). Brenon was publicity director for the Roxy Theatre, in Manhattan (opened 1927), and later worked for the Pathé Exchange, Cecil B. DeMille, and David O. Selznick film companies. The collection includes correspondence from Brenon's extended family, virtually all of whom had some connection to the arts, most notably her uncle, the silent film director Herbert Brenon (1880–1958), best known for "Beau Geste" (1926). Also present are several letters from Grant Wood (1891–1942), painter of "American Gothic," to Brenon's first husband, the art critic Thomas Jewell Craven (1888–1969).
Scope and Contents
The Aileen St. John-Brenon Papers contain correspondence, clippings, and ephemera spanning 1920 through 1947, with a significant number of undated letters (two folders worth). The collection documents Brenon's career as publicity manager of the Roxy Theatre, in Manhattan, which opened in 1927 (see box 1, folders 5-6), her work for the Pathé Exchange film company (see box 1, folder 11, for her publicity pieces on the 1930 film "Her Man"), and her involvement in the life and work of her first husband, the novelist and art critic Thomas Jewell Craven (see box 2, folder 5, for letters to Craven from painter Grant Wood of "American Gothic" fame). Since so many members of the St. John-Brenon family were involved in theatrical pursuits, most letters reference the arts. Frequent correspondents include Aileen's grandmother, the newspaper columnist Frances Brenon (1848–1931), and her uncle, silent film director Herbert Brenon (1880–1958). The collection holds two newspaper photographs of Aileen St. John-Brenon, one from 1923 (box 1, folder 1), the other from 1927 (box 3, folder 5).
Arrangement
The collection is divided into two series:
Series I. Dated material, 1920-1947--21 folders, sorted chronologically.
Series II. Undated and miscellaneous material, undated, 1927-1941--correspondence (2 folders); writings and publicity (1 folder); ephemera (2 folders); food and diet, 1927-1941 (1 folder).
Biographical/Historical Note
Aileen St. John-Brenon (1894–1967) was an American music critic, and theatrical and film publicist. She was born in England on 17 April 1894 and emigrated the following year with her parents, music critic Algernon St. John-Brenon (1875–1915), and Grace (Damian) St. John-Brenon (1869–1946), an oratorio singer who appeared at command performances before Queen Alexandra at Buckingham Palace. Aileen succeeded her father as music critic for the New York Morning Telegraph. Following that she directed publicity for the 1927 opening of the Roxy Theatre, Samuel "Roxy" Rothafel's 6,000-seat "cathedral of the motion picture" at 153 West 50th Street in Manhattan. (The Roxy was demolished in 1961.) Aileen moved on to film publicity, writing for Pathé Exchange (just before Joseph P. Kennedy sold it to R.K.O. in April 1930), Paramount, Cecil B. DeMille, and David O. Selznick. In the early 1950s, in partnership with Helen Morgan, she represented the performers Sophie Tucker and Judy Garland, and the film and theater director Rouben Mamoulian. Aileen retired in 1955 to travel with her second husband, playwright Richard Harrity (1907–1973), who was then travel editor for Cosmopolitan. Her first husband, whom she married in 1923 and divorced in 1947, was the novelist and art critic Thomas Jewell Craven (1888–1969), who championed the work of Thomas Hart Benton and Grant Wood. By her first husband Aileen had one son, Richard Craven (1928–2001). By her second husband she was stepmother to actor Rory Harrity (1933–1974). Aileen St. John-Brenon died in New York City on 23 September 1967, aged seventy-two.
In addition to her parents and both husbands, virtually every member of Aileen's extended family had some connection to the arts. Her grandmother, Frances (Harris) St. John-Brenon (1848–1931), was a traveler and author of the newspaper column "Things Quaint and Curious." (Oscar Wilde frequented her London salon.) Aileen's grandfather was the English dramatic critic Edward St. John-Brenon. Her uncle, Herbert Brenon (1880–1958), was a motion picture director perhaps best known for the silent films "Peter Pan" (1924) and "Beau Geste" (1926). Aileen's younger sister, Juliet St. John-Brenon (1895–1979), was an actress who appeared in some of their Uncle Herbert's films. Juliet married well-known set designer Cleon "Throck" Throckmorton (1897-1965), who maintained an active studio in bohemian Greenwich Village. An aunt, Roma (Brenon) Gurney (c. 1870–1927), was an actress, whose children, Oliver "Noll" Gurney and Hillary Gurney worked for the Cecil B. DeMille Film Company as production manager and secretary to the publicity manager.
[This note is drawn from several obituaries in the New York Times: "Algernon St. John-Brenon. Musical Critic of The Morning Telegraph Dies at Atlantic City" (20 December 1915); "Mrs. Frances Brenon Dies on Coast at 82" (14 July 1931); "Mrs. A. St. J. Brenon; Was Oratorio Singer" (2 October 1946); "Cleon Throckmorton, 68, Dead; Designed O'Neill Stage Settings" (25 October 1965); "Aileen Harrity, 72, A Publicity Woman" (24 September 1967); "Thomas Craven, Author, Dead; Caustic Art Critic and Lecturer" (1 March 1969); "Richard Harrity, Playwright, Dies" (21 January 1973); "Juliet B. Throckmorton" (22 November 1979).]
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Peter M. White, June 2016.
Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Motion picture theaters -- New York (State) -- New York.; Motion picture industry -- United States.; Musical criticism -- United States.; Ephemera.; Letters (correspondence); Publicity.; Brenon, Juliet, 1897-1979; Brenon, Herbert, 1880-1958; St. John-Brenon, Aileen, 1894-1967; Kennedy, Joseph P. (Joseph Patrick), 1888-1969; Harrity, Richard, 1907–1973; Craven, Thomas Jewell, 1888-1969; Wood, Grant, 1891-1942; Throckmorton, Cleon, 1897-1965; Rothafel, Samuel Lionel, 1881-1936; Roxy Theatre (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I. Dated material, 1920-1947
  - Correspondence, clippings, 1920-1923 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes a 1923 newspaper engagement notice with a photograph of Aileen St. John-Brenon.
  - Correspondence, clippings, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes letters on "Cecil B. De Mille Pictures Corporation" stationery, and a letter from theatrical impresario Samuel "Roxy" Rothafel.
  - Correspondence, clippings, ephemera, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, ephemera, publicity, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes an exchange, beginning in December, with Samuel "Roxy" Rothafel, regarding Aileen St. John-Brenon's discovery that she had been replaced as publicity manager during a trip to Europe.
    Also includes a broadside (6 December 1927) for Bill and Cobina Wright's "Circus" (for others, see box 1, folder 8).
  - Roxy Theatre publicity, clippings, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, ephemera, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes draft of last will and testament of Frances (Harris) St. John-Brenon (1848-1931), grandmother of Aileen (28 August 1928).
  - Correspondence, ephemera, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes two broadsides for Bill and Cobina Wright's "circus" at the Sherry-Netherland (5 January 1929; for another, see box 1, folder 5), and a broadside for a production of "The Black Crook" at the Lyric Theatre, Hoboken, New Jersey, with sets designed by Cleon Throckmorton, Aileen's brother-in-law (11 March 1929).
  - Correspondence, 1930 January-June (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, ephemera, 1930 July-December (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes a broadside announcing Herbert Brenon's "Beau Ideal," a sequel to his 1926 film "Beau Geste" (see 16 September 1930).
  - "Her Man" (film) publicity, [1930] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Scope and Contents Note
    "Her Man," a 1930 film retelling of the stage play "Frankie and Johnny," was directed by Tay Garnett and produced by Pathé Exchange. It starred Phillips Holmes, Helen Twelvetrees, and Marjorie Rambeau.
  - Talking pictures articles, [1930] (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Assorted pieces on the science of sound motion pictures, including a memo from Joseph P. Kennedy (father of President John F. Kennedy), in his role as chairman of Pathé Exchange, a film distribution company. With additional memos on Kennedy's retirement from the film industry and the sale of Pathé Exchange to R.K.O.
  - Correspondence, clippings, 1931 January-June (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, clippings, 1931 July-December (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes an obituary for Aileen's grandmother, the writer Frances (Harris) St. John-Brenon (1848-1931), from the New York Herald Tribune, Tuesday 14 July 1931.
  - Correspondence, 1933-1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes correspondence from painter Grant Wood (1891-1942), and Aileen St. John-Brenon's husband, the art critic and lecturer Thomas Jewell Craven (1888-1969). A letter from Noll Gurney, Aileen's cousin, mentions her "friend Harrity," presumably playwright Richard Harrity, her future second husband, whom she would marry after she divorced Craven in 1947.
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, clippings, ephemera, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes a list of Cleon Throckmorton's productions (23 May 1941).
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, ephemera, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1947 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series II. Undated and miscellaneous material, undated, 1927-1941
  - Correspondence (1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Of interest is a blueprint drawing invitation to a Christmas party at set designer Cleon Throckmorton's studio at 102 West 3rd Street in Greenwich Village.
  - Correspondence (2 of 2), undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Writings, publicity, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes an outline of Aileen St. John-Brenon's work for Pathé Exchange, Inc, during 1929.
  - Ephemera: Europe, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Items from England, France, and Italy.
  - Ephemera: Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Food and diet, 1927-1941 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    According to a clipping in this file (7 February 1927), which includes a photograph of her peeling a piece of fruit, Aileen St. John-Brenon enjoyed cooking. Includes some recipes and diet plans.